A poppy field before sunrise, cold enough to show breath.
The pods were scored the evening before and have wept their gum overnight; now a line of scrapers moves down the rows, lifting the grey beads off each pod with a curved iron before the dew burns away.
At the edge of the field, where the rows meet the earthen bund, lies a girl on her side in the dirt: LEELA, sixteen, a printed kameez gone stiff with dew, one slipper on and one in the furrow beside her.
An old woman scrapes the row nearest the body without looking at it, her lips going Ram Ram, Ram Ram, her iron not stopping; a boy works behind her.
A CBN jeep pulls onto the field road.
INSPECTOR RATAN SINGH PANWAR, fifties, heavy, a sweater under his uniform, gets out slowly with a hand on the door.
Constable DEVA, twenty-four, follows a step behind and stays there.
BHERULAL, the girl's father, comes across the field toward them but stops a few rows short of the body.
You've come, sahib. At night... who knows why she went out. It was dark. She must have fallen. That's all. Just make out the papers, I'll sign.
He still has not looked at her.
Who saw her first?
The scrapers. They came before dawn... she was lying here. I let no one touch her. She's just as she was.
Ratan crouches beside the girl, slow, a hand on his knee.
Deva photographs from the bund.
Bherulal turns away, toward the field.
She was engaged?
Yes. The boy's people were coming in two days to fix the wedding date. If word spreads now...
Ratan stands and looks at the scrapers still working the rows around the body.
You've kept the work going.
The gum doesn't wait, sahib. Should I... should I just stand here?
Ratan looks at the field a moment, then turns to Deva.
Clear the field. No scraping today.
Deva goes.
Down the field the scrapers stop and stand, holding their irons over the gum.
Bherulal comes after Ratan.
Don't stop it, sahib. Don't do this. If the crop doesn't come in... sahib, you know. I have nothing else...
Ratan looks at him.
Call two more men from the station. No — call four. And send the body to the district hospital for postmortem. We stay here today.
Postmortem? Sahib, she died from a fall. Don't put her through more... just... let her be.
He does not look at the father.
It's the rule.
Bherulal keeps at him — sahib, think once more — but Ratan has crouched back down beside the girl, and he stays there, and after a while the pleading stops on its own.
A small room off the women's side, thin light through one barred window.
The whole house smells of the gum, in the walls and in the dead girl's clothes.
A string cot, a steel almirah, Leela's Class 10 guidebooks tied with string for the boards three weeks off.
In the next room a woman's voice goes up — Oh my darling, oh my child — and the others take it up.
SUGNA sits on the floor with her daughter's clothes in her lap, her shoulders shaking, a fold of the girl's clothes pressed to her mouth.
RATAN fills the doorway.
He steps in and goes to the almirah.
Sugna's head comes up.
What are you doing... these are my child's things.
An AUNT comes in behind him.
Sahib, step outside. This is the women's room.
Ratan does not stop.
He works the lid off a steel tin, and under a fold of cloth finds a smaller cloth knotted tight: a thin roll of tens and twenties and a fist of one-rupee coins, and a coaching-class handbill from Ratlam, soft at the folds from handling.
Sugna has got to her feet and reached him, pulling at his arm, at the clothes in his hands.
My darling... my child...
Ratan looks at the handbill a moment, then folds the cloth back over the money and puts it in his pocket.
The aunt comes and takes Sugna by the arm, and Sugna folds against her and lets herself be held.
He goes, out through the keening.
A government room gone yellow at the edges — steel almirahs of files, a ceiling fan turning slow, a framed Gandhi over the door.
SUPERINTENDENT MISHRA sits behind his desk with Leela's thin file open in front of him.
Ratan stands.
DEVA waits by the door.
She fell in the field and died, and it's licensed land. The father's ready to sign. What's so much in this, Ratan?
I've sent the body for postmortem.
Mishra looks up.
Who sent it?
I did.
Mishra sits back, the tiredness of a man who has settled a hundred of these.
She's a village girl. There's a death in the house, it's a matter of honour. What will you get from cutting her open? Write the report, close it. I'll sign right now.
The father wouldn't leave the crop, sahib. His child lay in front of him, and he was thinking about the harvest.
Every father's in a hurry. Ratan. Whose licenses run this belt, who stands behind whom — who knows it better than you? Don't put your hand into someone's house for nothing.
Ratan does not answer that.
The report comes after the postmortem.
Mishra holds his eye a moment, then drops it back to the file.
Fine. Your report, your responsibility.
Ratan turns to go.
Deva follows him out.
Ratan lowers himself into his chair.
Deva hovers, the file still in his hands.
Sahib... Mishra sahib isn't wrong. She must have slipped and fallen.
Have you ever seen anyone slip and die in a poppy field?
...No.
Neither have I.
A beat.
Ratan does not go on with it.
Order tea, Deva.
The field at the end of the day, the lancing stopped on Ratan's order, the gum drying grey and useless on the pods.
Ratan walks the bund where the body lay, Deva a step behind with a torch he does not need yet.
At the field's edge, a well.
The house two hundred metres off, its one light on.
The house is there. She was found here, at this end of the field.
What would she come to this end for, at night?
Ratan looks past the well, to a footpath running off into the dark.
Where does this path go?
To the road. The bus stand's ahead — the Manasa one.
Ratan stands a while where the path leaves the field.
Who saw her last that night — at home, in the field, on the path. Ask everyone. Write down the names.
An old NIGHT-WATCHMAN sits on a charpai outside a hut, a stick across his knees.
Deva has brought him to Ratan.
He is careful, an old man who has kept his job by not seeing things.
Were you on watch that night?
I was, sahib. My eyes shut for a bit in between.
Did you see Leela? Bherulal's girl.
The old man looks at the stick across his knees.
...I saw her. Late at night. Alone, walking fast, toward the road.
Crying? Frightened?
It was so dark, sahib. She was just in a hurry. Whether anyone was behind her, I didn't see. I went back to sleep.
Would anyone else have seen?
I don't know. Sahib, don't put my name on any paper. I have to live here.
A small farming household — a kitchen open to the courtyard, a hand-pump, the smell of frying onion.
DEVA's mother, AMMA, works the dough.
His father, BAPU, sits on a charpai.
SUNITA, eighteen, Deva's sister, moves between them with the food.
DEVA comes in from the day still in uniform.
You're back. Wash up. Listen — Girdhari's son, Vijay. His family's proposing for Sunita.
It's a good household. Two bigha of land, a license too. The boy's looking for work in the city.
Sunita sets a bowl down and does not look up.
Go meet them once. You're in uniform — your word carries weight.
I'm caught up in a case right now, Amma.
Cases will keep coming. The girl's age is slipping by. Well? You say something.
Whatever you think is right.
Deva looks at his sister.
The day is still on him.
Did anyone ask Sunita?
What's there to ask, son? It's a good match. We wouldn't wish her ill.
Sunita's eyes come up to Deva's for a second — and go back down to the food.
So go and meet them. Day after tomorrow.
...I'll see.
Sunita carries the empty pot to the pump and works the handle, and the water covers whatever she does not say.
The house asleep, one low bulb still on in the corner where SUNITA has her bedding.
She sits up with a school notebook open in her lap and a pen in her hand, not writing.
From the parents' room, the murmur of the match goes on — Girdhari's boy, two bigha, a license.
She listens to it the way you listen to weather.
Deva comes in for water, sees her awake.
Go to sleep.
Will you go to meet them? Day after? Them?
I'll see.
Sunita closes the notebook and lies down, her face to the wall.
Leave it. Everything's fine.
Deva stands with the glass in his hand and does not drink it.
A line of licensed growers waits with their season's gum in steel lotas.
At the scale sits KHARE, the measurement officer, fifty and neat, weighing a farmer's lump of latex and writing the figure into a register.
A FARMER watches the needle like his life is on it.
It's short. Less than last time, even. Mind it next time.
The farmer takes his receipt and goes, not arguing.
Ratan has come up at the side.
Khare sees him, and a practised warmth comes on.
Ah, Ratan sahib. I heard about Bherulal's girl.
Does Bherulal give full weight here?
The pen stops for half a second.
The girl fell and died, sahib. What's Bherulal's license got to do with that?
I'm just asking.
Khare leans in, the practised warmth gone, his voice dropped.
Ratan. Bherulal's in debt, and whose debt it is, you know too. Everyone's accounts are running even here. Don't stick your leg in the middle.
A girl is dead, Khare.
Khare goes back to his register and the next man's lota.
Girls keep dying around here.
A roadside stall, a kettle, men on a bench with glasses of tea, the bazaar behind.
The talk is the dead girl.
They do not lower their voices much.
Heard about it? Bherulal's girl. At night, in the field.
What was she doing in the field at night — nobody asks that. Girls these days.
She was engaged, wasn't she? Into a good family?
She was. God's will.
A third man, older, has been quiet.
The CBN man's nosing around. Had a postmortem done.
Will he let it go? These people have reach right to the top. Ratan sahib is sensible. He'll get it closed.
They drink their tea.
Tiles, a steel table, a drain.
Leela's body under a sheet.
The medical officer, DOCTOR VERMA, fills a form standing up, wanting to be elsewhere.
Ratan and Deva at the door.
Head injury, from the fall. It's clear. I'm writing 'brought dead'.
Did you send the viscera?
What for? The injury's right there.
Lungs, stomach, blood — send all of it.
Inspector, four bodies come here every day. If I sent everyone's viscera the lab would collapse. Has something been said from above?
If it had, the word would be to stop it, not to send it.
Verma looks at him, then at the small shape under the sheet.
He folds the sheet back from her face and leans in, and something stops him a moment.
The injury is from a fall, but... all right, I'll send it. The report will take a week to ten days.
Get it done quickly.
Another grower's plot, another lancing crew.
The grower, HUKMA, walks Ratan along his rows, easy, the two of them old at this.
At the end of the row Hukma folds a few notes into Ratan's hand the way you'd pass a relative something for the children, and Ratan takes them the way you take it, without looking.
If the weighing runs a little off this time... well, you're there, sahib.
We'll see to it.
That Bherulal business... it'll all be set right, won't it?
Ratan does not answer that.
He pockets the notes and walks back to the jeep, and for a second he stands at the door with his hand on it, not getting in.
The jeep pulled over on an empty country road.
Ratan stands at the edge of a field that is not part of his case — a good plot, well worked, someone's gum drying on the racks.
He looks at it the way a man looks at a house he used to live in.
A YOUNG FARMER slows his motorcycle, sees the uniform, folds his hands.
Ram Ram, sahib.
Ram Ram.
Ratan looks at the field a moment longer, then gets back in the jeep, and it goes dark behind him.
The condolence crowd has thinned.
DAULATRAM, fifty-five, the groom's uncle, prosperous and unhurried, sits where the mourners sat.
Behind him stands PRATAP, forty, the groom, saying nothing.
Bherulal receives them with both hands.
Very bad business, Bherulal. Who can turn aside what's fated? But we must speak of what's ahead too.
Yes, of course. The bond between us will hold, Daulatram-ji.
The girl is gone. And the accounts that stood — the debt, the land — those were tied to the match.
The debt... I'll repay it. Just a little time.
Daulatram lets that sit.
Then, easily:
How old is your younger one?
Something goes across Bherulal's face.
His elder girl is not yet in the ground.
...Twelve.
When she's older, we'll talk. Keep the accounts square.
Pratap looks at the house a moment — the dead girl's house — with flat eyes, and follows his uncle out.
Bherulal stands where they left him.
The women's side.
An older relative, the AUNT, sorts through Leela's things into a cloth bundle to be given away, the way it is done.
Bherulal's younger daughter, NANHI, twelve, sits against the wall watching.
SUGNA is on the floor, not helping, her hands in her lap.
The aunt holds up a kameez, decides, folds it into the bundle.
What will you do keeping these? They'll serve someone in need.
Sugna says nothing.
Nanhi watches a green dupatta go into the bundle.
That's my sister's.
Yes, child. Your sister isn't here anymore.
Nanhi looks at her mother.
Sugna does not look back at her, or at the bundle, or at anything.
Her hands stay folded in her lap as the last of the girl goes into the cloth.
Mishra is on the phone, listening far more than he speaks, his face gone careful.
He puts it down.
Ratan is at the door.
Ratan. Come in. A call just came. From above.
From whom?
They were asking why the Bherulal matter still isn't closed.
Let the report come, sahib.
Mishra comes around the desk, and what is in his voice now is almost kindness.
Twenty-five years you've served. Two years left, your pension in sight. For one dead girl you'll take on the men at the top? They'll ruin you in a single stroke. Do you understand?
I understand.
Then close it.
Let the report come.
Mishra looks at him a long moment, the way you look at a man walking into something, and lets him go.
A narrow lane, a wall, the back of the government school.
RESHMA, sixteen, in school uniform, walking fast with her bag.
Ratan falls in beside her.
She does not stop.
You were Leela's friend. Reshma.
I don't know anything, sahib.
He holds out the Ratlam handbill, folded soft.
This was with her. A coaching slip, from Ratlam. I haven't come to trap her, child. I've come to learn what happened.
Reshma slows.
She looks back down the empty lane once.
She wanted to study. Further. Go to Ratlam. She was saving money, in secret.
In secret from whom?
From her family. Her marriage was fixed — to that man who was much older. Leela used to say: I won't go there. I'll run, I'll study.
The lane is quiet.
Reshma's eyes fill, and she wipes them with the back of her wrist, angry at it.
Sahib, don't tell anyone my name. I have to go.
Did anyone help her? To run?
But she has already pulled her bag up and gone, fast, the way you go when you have said one word too many.
The jeep on a dark road, the fields black on both sides.
Deva drives.
Ratan beside him, the day behind his eyes.
She was running. From the very man she was promised to. Forty years old.
Forty. And Leela sixteen.
They drive a while.
Sahib... there's talk for my sister too. Good boy, land, a license. I'm to go meet them, day after tomorrow.
Did your sister say yes?
Deva opens his mouth to answer, and finds he does not have one.
...I don't know.
Ratan looks out at the dark fields and does not say anything, and lets the boy sit with it.
Morning, the family at tea.
BAPU is dressed to go — the visit to the boy's family is today.
AMMA presses a clean shirt on Deva.
Sunita pours, eyes down.
Come on, Deva, it's getting late. Girdhari will be waiting.
Deva does not get up.
Bapu. Did we ask her? Sunita?
The room stops a little.
Bapu turns.
What kind of talk is this?
We just ask. Once. You say it. Do you want to go?
Sunita's hand stays on the kettle.
The whole house waits on her, and for a moment it is not certain what she will say.
A small house.
Ratan eats alone at the table.
His wife, KANTA, clears a pot in the back, the two of them long past needing to speak.
A knock.
At the door, A MAN — pressed shirt, calm, the kind that is never quite introduced.
Ratan sahib. Forgive the late hour. Two minutes.
He steps in only as far as he needs to, and sets a thick envelope on the edge of the table.
The Bherulal matter. There's a wish from above that it close quickly. An accident, that's all. And this — for your trouble.
Ratan looks at the envelope.
He has taken a hundred of these.
Kanta, in the back, does not turn around.
Whose wish?
You're a sensible man.
The envelope sits between them.
It would be the easiest thing in the world.
Then Ratan slides it back across the table.
Not this time.
The smile goes.
Think it over, sahib. This road won't be good for you.
It's gotten very late.
The man takes his envelope and goes.
Ratan sits.
After a while Kanta speaks from the back, not unkind, not hopeful.
What fight are you picking at this age?
Ratan does not answer her.
He looks at the door the man left by.
Late, the office empty.
Ratan sits with Leela's thin file open under the lamp.
Her school photo is clipped to the corner — a girl grinning crooked at a camera, a board exam three weeks off.
He looks at it for a long time.
The mourners are gone.
The house is dark.
SUGNA sits alone against the wall where the women keened all day, her daughter's folded clothes in her lap, her hands still on them.
The camera holds on her, on her hands on the folded clothes, and does not move either.