There is no establishing shot. We are close to him, and the
only light is the fire. An old hand, bloody to the wrist,
closes on the worn grip of a sword. The blade is old
and notched in a hundred places, and on one finger sits a
heavy gold signet, its mark almost rubbed smooth. The blade goes forward
into a man we never see, and a shape twists away into
the dark. On one side there is fire, and men keep coming
out of it. The old hand turns the sword to meet them,
and meets them again. For half a breath the view opens: an
old man on dark ground, the smoke behind him lit saffron, the
blood to his elbow, more men closing in — and he does
not go down.
CUT TO BLACK.
A low government building the colour of the dust around it, the
paint peeling off the board outside, a CBN jeep up on bricks
with one wheel gone. A shared tempo pulls away in a cloud
of grit and DEVA steps down with an iron trunk on his
shoulder, his uniform still creased from the shop. He stands and takes
the place in, and it is not what he pictured on the
bus.
Inside, a MUNSHI sits behind a register under a slow fan, a
glass of tea going cold by his elbow. He does not look
up when the door's shadow falls across his book.
Constable Deva. Transferred from Itarsi. I'm to report to Ratan Singh Panwar,
sir.
Sahib's out on rounds.
I see. When will he be back?
He'll come.
Deva waits for more. There is no more. He sets the trunk
down, then thinks better of it and keeps standing.
Should I... wait here? Or the quarters—
Sit.
He sits on the bench. A KISAN comes in past him, a
man who has been here before and knows the order of things.
He lays a folded note on the open register and slides it
across without a word. The munshi takes it under his palm, stamps
a paper, and turns it around for the farmer to lift. It
is done in seconds. The farmer touches his forehead and goes.
Deva watches the note go under the blotter, and is not sure
what he just saw.
That... what did he give that for?
Tea money.
For what, though?
The munshi looks up at him for the first time, then goes
back to his register.
Deva sits back down. He watches the stamped paper go out the
door in the farmer's hand, and says nothing.
RATAN comes in heavy and unhurried, the khaki gone shapeless on him,
and lowers himself into the chair behind the desk as if it
costs him something. Deva is on his feet at once.
Sir. Constable Deva. I've been posted under you.
Ratan looks at him — the new uniform, the open face —
for a second longer than nothing, and then it is put away.
He pulls the day's files toward him. A second KISAN is already
at the desk, turning his cap in his hands, a thin file
in front of him.
Yes.
Sir, the tractor turned over in the night, on my elder brother.
Just write that it was an accident. There's mourning at home, sir
— we want nothing else.
Ratan opens the file. He does not read it. He signs.
Done. Go.
The farmer sets a small fold of notes by the inkpad and
is gone before it lands. Ratan moves it under the blotter with
two fingers, the way the munshi did, without looking at it. Deva
has watched all of it.
Sir... won't there be a postmortem?
For whom?
A man's dead, sir. At least take a look—
And what will looking get you?
...I don't know. But the rules—
Someone dies here every day. If I did a postmortem on each,
nothing else would ever get done.
He looks at Deva properly now, and does not look away as
fast as he might.
You're from Itarsi, aren't you.
Yes, sir.
They don't grow opium there.
Opium? You mean... really?
It's the crop here, on a government licence. The whole district runs
on it. Look too hard and the first thing you'll lose is
your job.
Deva does not answer. Ratan has already pulled the next file toward
him.
A narrow shop hung with other men's pledges — brass, a radio,
a woman's set of bangles on a nail. The SAHUKAR sits behind
a low counter with a small cloth bundle in front of him,
which he does not open. Off to the side, on a stool,
sits CHARAN — very old, one eye gone milky — who has
come, it seems, only to be in the room with the thing
in the cloth.
The interest keeps mounting, Singh sahib. It's not me saying it —
the ledgers say it.
Ratan lays down what notes he has on the counter. The sahukar
looks at them, and does not pick them up.
This is barely half the interest.
The rest next month.
I hear the same thing every month, sahib. A jeweller came last
week. It's an old signet, the gold is heavy — he'll pay
well. I've held it back out of respect for you. But how
long?
Ratan says nothing. He looks at the cloth and not at it.
That signet is not a thing to be sold, seth.
Charan baba, don't start again.
That signet is heavy with the blood of ancestors, not with gold.
Listen, son. They were of Raja Bhoj's line — Parmar, Panwar. Khilji's
storm broke on this very soil, seven hundred years ago. The whole
fort fell. And one had his head severed from his body, and
still the sword kept moving. Fallen, he did not fall. That signet
is from his finger.
The sahukar has heard it before and looks away, embarrassed for the
old man. Ratan has heard it before too. He does not turn
around. He pushes the half-payment an inch further across the counter, the
most he can do, and walks out into the light. For a
moment his right hand hangs at his side — the finger where
the ring used to sit is bare, with a pale band still
on the skin.
A SIPAHI comes in off the road, dust to the knees, and
puts a thin file on the desk — barely a page in
it.
This morning, near Koteshwar, a girl was found at the edge of
a field, sir.
Whose?
From the big house. Must have fallen in the night, in the
dark. The family says settle it quickly — there's a wedding coming,
word mustn't spread.
Which big house?
Bherulal seth's.
The name means nothing to Ratan. He does not open the file.
Deva, beside him, looks down at the closed cover.
A girl, was it?
She was. Now she isn't.
Put it on the pile.
Deva looks at the single thin page that is all there is
of her. The sipahi sets the file on the day's pile and
goes back out to the road.
The light has gone amber. The pile has come down to the
last file, the thin one. Ratan opens the cover, reads to the
end of the first line, and uncaps his pen.
Sir. Should we go and look, just once? Koteshwar's close. Half an
hour.
She fell.
You haven't even seen it, and—
There's the constable's report, isn't there.
But sir, it's a girl, it's a big house's matter — if
someone asks tomorrow—
No one will ask.
He says it flat, certain, the certainty of a man who knows
exactly who asks questions in this district and who does not. He
writes the cause across the form, caps the pen, and closes the
file without ever turning to the name on the second page. The
day's fold of notes goes into his breast pocket. He stands, tired,
and reaches for his cap.
Deva starts to say something and stops himself. He watches the day's
notes go into Ratan's pocket, and this time he stays quiet.
A small kept house, everything in its place and nothing new in
years. KANTA sets a plate in front of him and straightens, a
hand on her back. On the side table, an opened government envelope.
The pension papers came today. The office called as well. Two more
years.
Ratan sits. He turns his hand over and looks at the pale
band where the ring used to be, then at the plate. He
does not start eating.
Two years and you'll be home all day. I keep wondering what
you'll do with yourself. You were never one to sit at home.
I'll eat your cooking.
Don't sweet-talk me. Eat — it's going cold.
He eats. She stands a moment longer than she needs to, looking
at the top of his bent head from across the small kitchen,
across a distance that has grown over the years without either of
them deciding it. Then she takes the envelope off the side table
and puts it away in a drawer, where the other unspoken things
are kept.
The pyre has caught. Not many have come — a handful of
old men, a son with his head freshly shaved, a dog keeping
its distance. A singer works through a Nirgun bhajan, the kind sung
where there is no idol and no comfort to be had from
the words. RATAN stands at the edge with his hands behind his
back. GOVIND, his own age, stands next to him and watches the
fire instead of the body.
There were four of us, remember? You, me, him, and Kailash. Now
there are two left.
Mm.
Look how many came. Three months ago the man was in uniform,
gave the orders. He retired, and everyone forgot. Today there aren't even
enough to carry the pyre.
Ratan watches the smoke go up and does not answer. Govind is
quiet a while, then says the thing more softly, not to wound,
just because it is in him.
Who'll remember us, Ratan? A few years, and we're this same ash.
No son, no name — no one to ask what kind of
man he was.
Ratan looks down at his own hands. He does not say anything.
The others have gone. The pyre is down to embers. Govind crouches
and feeds a last stick into it, more for something to do
than for the fire. Ratan stands as if he means to leave
and does not.
Remember Chambal?
Let it go now, Govind.
No, listen. When you went alone into the ravines, after those dacoits.
The whole station stood outside, wetting their trousers, and you went in.
And by evening you brought them out tied up. Alone. Your photo
was in the paper.
That was many years ago. A different man.
Exactly. You were different, Ratan. The rest of us joined for the
wages. There was something else in you. A man doesn't really change,
brother. He just gets buried, on top. The earth covers him. But
underneath, he's the same.
Ratan looks at his hands again. Govind lets it sit; he has
said it before and he will say it again, and they both
know it. Ratan turns to go. At the road, where one way
runs home and the other toward Koteshwar, he stands a moment. Then
he takes the road to Koteshwar.
The place has been walked over by everyone who came to look
and to settle it — sandal-prints, a tractor's tread, the dragged smear
where they lifted her. A few villagers stop their work to watch
the old inspector who never comes to a scene now standing at
one, in no hurry, looking at the dirt.
Who found her?
A young CHARVAHA (herder), hanging back, answers because Ratan is looking at
him.
I did, sir. In the morning, I'd brought the buffalo. She was
lying right here.
Which way was she facing?
Face down. Below the bund.
Ratan crouches at the bund and puts his hand flat on top
of it. It comes up to his knee. He looks at it
a long time. He looks at the dry, hard earth, and at
the distance to the well across the field, and at the bund
again. He has not worked a scene in twenty-five years. He works
this one.
A bund knee-high.
Sir?
Nothing.
A older KISAN, sensing the wrong kind of attention coming to the
village, speaks up, helpful, eager to close it.
She must have fallen in the dark, sir. Felt dizzy, maybe. Girls
are weak.
Ratan does not look up from the ground. A girl does not
trip over a thing she could step across and break her skull
on flat dirt. He stays crouched there, reading it, until the kisan
runs out of things to say and the field goes quiet around
him.
Ratan pulls the thin file back off the closed pile and opens
it on the desk. The MUNSHI watches over his register, not understanding,
then understanding and not liking it.
Sir, that was closed yesterday. You signed it off yourself.
I'm opening it again.
For a postmortem? Sir, it's a big house's matter. Bherulal seth's. He
sent word himself to settle it fast.
So?
So... nothing, sir. Just... word will reach the top.
Ratan takes a fresh requisition form, writes the order across it in
his own hand, and signs it. He blots it and turns it
to face the munshi.
Send it today. The district hospital here, to Dr. Bhanwar.
The munshi looks at the form, and at the inspector who has
signed papers in this room for fifteen years and never once asked
for a postmortem on anything. He picks it up as if it
might be hot. Across the room, DEVA, at the wall, watches the
man amend his own signature, and something in his face that had
been going out comes back a little.
MISHRA sits behind a clean desk, a neat man, a pressed uniform,
a glass of water and no files. He waves Ratan to a
chair with real warmth, the warmth of a man who has never
had to raise his voice to get his way.
Arre, sit, Ratan, sit. Shall I send for tea? Listen, this Koteshwar
file. You've sent it for a postmortem?
I have.
Twenty-five years of service, yaar. Two left. And you, over a girl
who fell — what for? Tell me, what's the matter?
The bund was knee-high.
So? People die falling from knee height too, if the head hits
wrong. Look. The file was closed. Let it stay closed. Do your
two years in peace, take your pension, go home. What's in this
mess — one girl, a big house, reach to the very top.
Let it go, brother. Not for me — for yourself.
It's done, Mishra. The file's gone.
For a moment the warmth is not quite there in Mishra's face.
Then it comes back, smooth.
Gone. All right. Have your tea before you go.
Ratan stands and goes without the chai. Mishra watches the door a
moment, then picks up the phone.
A black stone face under a heap of marigold and silver foil,
fierce, smeared with vermilion. The PUJARI takes a bottle of country liquor,
tips it into the shallow silver dish set below the god's mouth,
and the level in the dish drops as they watch. DEVA, a
step behind Ratan, stares at it.
Sir... it's... going down.
It's Kaal Bhairav, son. The kotwal of Avanti. Flowers don't move him
much. No sweets, no recommendations. Only this — liquor. And whoever lies
before him, he settles the account himself. He needs no police station.
animal he respects)* इन पे फूल-पत्ती नहीं चढ़ती ज़्यादा। न मिठाई, न
सिफ़ारिश। बस यही — दारू। और जो झूठ बोले इनके सामने, उसका
हिसाब ये ख़ुद लेते हैं। किसी थाने की ज़रूरत नहीं।
Ratan and Deva go lane to lane, and the lanes close as
they come. A man remembers a buffalo to see to. A woman
pulls a child inside. Doors that were open find reasons to be
half-shut. The trade has taught this village to have nothing to say
to a uniform that is actually asking.
At last an old WOMAN, sweeping a doorstep, talks — because she
is too old to be afraid of anyone, and because nobody important
listens to her anyway.
You police have come now? The girl was burned yesterday.
Mother, was there talk of her marriage?
Talk! It was fixed. To Dhanraj seth.
Dhanraj? But... I've heard he's an old man.
Sixty, son, not a day less. But here they don't look at
age. They look at standing. Bherulal had debt on the house —
the licence quota hasn't been met for two years. So hand the
girl over against the debt, into the old man's house. That's how
it goes.
Deva turns to look at Ratan, the wrongness of it sitting on
his young face. Ratan has gone still — the particular stillness of
a man into whom one piece has just slid against another. He
does not say what he is thinking. He thanks the old woman
and turns back toward the road.
A small, warm, plain room, lit by one tube-light. AMMA presses a
second roti onto Deva's plate before the first is gone. MANJU sits
to the side, her eyes down, a girl who is being discussed.
Eat, eat. You've gone thin. And listen, the boy's photo came from
Rajasthan. Good family, well-off. Manju will rule the house there. It's just
across the border, but there's a direct bus, three hours.
Deva looks at his sister. He has spent the whole day learning
what a girl is worth in this belt, and the word
Manju. Have you seen the photo? Did it... seem all right to
you?
Whatever you all think best, brother.
I'm asking you. You.
Manju glances at her mother, then down again, and says nothing, which
is its own answer. Amma fills the silence the way mothers do.
Oh, what are you asking her for. She's shy. You just do
your job properly, the rest takes care of itself.
Deva starts to say something — about old men and young girls
and what a marriage can be made to mean — and lets
it go. This match is a good one; it is not a
sale. And still he cannot get the day out of his mouth.
The report is already back. The same day it went out. The
MUNSHI hands it across almost apologetically. Ratan reads it: typed, stamped, two
lines — death consistent with a fall, no foul play indicated. He
holds it and does not put it down.
The same day?
The doctor was quick, sir. Said it's your case, not to hold
it up.
Ratan has handed Dr. Bhanwar a dozen reports like this over the
years, and not one of them ever took less than a week,
because a real postmortem takes a week. He knows exactly what a
same-day clean report is, in his hands, in his ink. He spent
twenty-five years making them. The clean page does not close the girl's
death for him. It opens everything standing behind it.
He folds the report into his pocket, and for once he is
not tired in the way he is usually tired.
DR. BHANWAR SINGH does not get up. A tired, clean-shaven man in
a pressed shirt, a Rajput of Ratan's own age and kind, with
a room that smells of phenyl and old paper.
You'll have got the report. It's clean. Death by a fall.
How did it come back clean the same day, Bhanwar?
It was done by the rules. The same rules for twenty-five years,
Singh sahib. And this many of your cases were closed by these
same rules. Not once did you ask 'how, the same day.' What's
changed today?
I don't know.
flat)* और तेरे भी इतने केस इसी नियम से बंद हुए हैं।
एक बार भी तूने नहीं पूछा "उसी दिन कैसे।" आज क्या बदल
गया?
Go home, Singh sahib. You've two years left. Don't ruin them for
a dead girl. She isn't coming back — and neither are you.
It is the truest thing he has said in years, and it
costs him to say it out loud. Bhanwar hears it. He does
not soften — that is Mishra's trade, not his — he answers
flat, the way he reads out a cause of death.
No paper will help him now. Every paper in the district lies,
and he knows it, because he taught it how. So he does
the thing he has not done in twenty-five years. He goes out
among the field hands at the end of the day, on foot,
off the books, and asks — whose girl, whose house, who saw
her last. They are afraid of the asking, and of him, and
of the big house, all at once.
Were you in the field that night?
I know nothing, sir. I'm a labouring man. I come at dawn,
I leave at dusk.
I'm not trapping you. I'm only asking.
The hand looks at him a long moment, weighing the old inspector
against the thing everyone in the village has already agreed to forget.
Then, quietly, giving him only the smallest true thing:
It's a big house over there, sir. Bherulal seth's. It's their matter.
Don't ask me.
The name is still nothing to Ratan. He turns and looks across
the darkening fields at the big house standing at the end of
them, lit up, and he walks toward it.
A prosperous house, gold in the doorway, a generator humming somewhere. Ratan
comes up the steps with his cap in his hand — a
policeman come to ask a family about a dead girl. He knocks.
There are feet inside, and a bolt drawn back, and the door
opens.
It is SUGNA.
Twenty-five years. Neither of them moves. Somewhere inside the house a woman
is crying and stops.
Now you come.
...Sugna.
She looks at the cap in his hands, and the khaki, and
back at his face.
You've come in uniform. To ask questions.
I didn't know this was your house. I'm telling the truth, Sugna.
I didn't—
When did you ever know anything.
He has no answer to that, the way he has had no
answer to it for twenty-five years. Behind her the house is dim,
full of people sitting in the heavy quiet that comes after a
death. On a shelf by the door, a girl's things — a
school bag, a comb, a folded dupatta, set aside the way you
set aside what you cannot yet put away. He looks at them,
and at his sister's closed face, and it begins to come.
Whose... whose girl was she?
Sugna's jaw works. She will not say it. From inside, an AUNT's
voice, taking the policeman at the door for only a policeman:
The name goes into him and does not stop. Leela was his
sister's daughter. He read the first line of that file and signed
it a fall and never turned to the name on the second
page; he took the day's money and went home and ate his
dinner.
He cannot say it. She stands and watches him not say it.
BHERULAL fills the inner doorway then — heavy, still, taking in the
brother-in-law in the uniform standing at his door at the worst hour
he could have come.
I...
You what?
She steps back from the door — not to let him in,
but because she is done holding it open — and turns into
the mourning house, and leaves him on the step with her husband's
eyes on him.
Who is it? ...Oh.
My brother. He's in the police. Hasn't come in twenty-five years. Today
he's come.
A side room, away from the mourners. Bherulal sits Ratan down and
sits across from him. He is not grieving in front of Ratan;
he is working out a problem, and Ratan is the problem.
Twenty-five years you didn't show your face at this house. You're Sugna's
brother, and you didn't come for the wedding, didn't come when the
daughters were born, nothing. And today, this very night, here you are.
In uniform.
How did the girl die, Bherulal?
What's done is done. Leela's gone. What comes back from that? Now
if the police come, a postmortem, word spreads — whose loss is
it? Your sister's. This house's. The little one, four years old. The
licence is to be made in his name next year. For that
the family name must be clean. You don't sink a living child's
future for a dead girl.
आए, कुछ नहीं। *(he lets that sit)* और आज, इसी रात, चले
आए। वर्दी पहन के।
Accidents keep happening in these parts, sir. A man goes out at
night, the bike slips, that's all. It happens. You know that well
enough.
Ratan says nothing. From the side, by the door, one of Bherulal's
MEN speaks — easy, flat, the way you'd mention the weather.
A glass of doda water goes cold at his elbow — the
poppy-husk brew he drinks to put the days down. Tonight it does
not work. On the table in front of him are two papers.
One is the clean report, his way out, the honourable one: he
did his duty, it is official, he can stop now and keep
his pension and his life. The other is a blank requisition form.
He turns his hand over. The pale band where the ring used
to be is white in the lamplight. Down the passage, KANTA appears
in her doorway in her nightclothes and sees him sitting up over
papers at this hour, which he has not done in years. She
does not ask. She knows the shape of him well enough to
know it is not a thing he will say. She goes back
in and the light under her door goes out.
He does not pick up the pen for a long time. Outside,
the night thins toward grey. And then, near morning, he picks it
up.
The post is empty and grey, the fan still. Ratan writes out
a fresh requisition by hand — a second postmortem, this one at
the district headquarters hospital two hundred kilometres away, out of Bhanwar's reach,
and Mishra's, and the big house's. At the bottom he does not
press the office stamp into it. He signs it himself, his own
name, in full, the way a man signs a thing he means
to stand behind.
DEVA comes in early, the dawn grey behind him, and stops when
he sees the old man already at the desk. He sees what
the requisition is, and the name on it, and what it will
cost. He does not say anything. He stands a little straighter.
Ratan caps the pen and sets it down. He has the look
of a man who has finally decided something.
CUT TO BLACK.