Behind the hospital, a low building. A tin door, the smell
of phenyl and melting ice. A tempo stands outside, loaded with
a bolt of white cloth and pyre wood. Three or four
men from the big house stand at the door. Bherulal's man
is talking, cold-eyed, in no hurry. The morgue compounder stands clutching
his register to his chest.
Doctor Bhanwar wrote 'death by fall' just yesterday and closed the
case. Now hand over the body, the mother's waiting outside.
Sahib, a new order came from above this morning. The body's
not to be released to anyone.
New order? The file was closed yesterday.
It came with Panwar sahib's signature, that the body goes to
the district headquarters for a second post-mortem. How can I release
it on my own?
The man reads the register slowly, down to the name written
at the bottom. Then he takes a wad of notes from
his vest and lays it on the open register.
Take this, and write that the family took the body. You've
got the doctor's clean paper already.
The compounder doesn't earn this much in a year. But his
hand stays where it is.
Panwar sahib's coming himself, sahib. You'll get me in trouble.
A woman's wailing rises from the corridor, and the other women
hush her. The man looks at the cloth and wood in
the tempo, then at the tin door.
Think about it. We need the body by evening. Let the
mother cremate her daughter.
He walks back to his people. The compounder stands holding the
register, the notes still on it. And Ratan's been standing at
the door long enough to have heard everything. He looks at
the tin door, then at the money on the register, and
says nothing.