That world, where Ratan hasn't yet arrived. Rana sits on his
swing, a line of people with folded hands before him, tea
going round. He grants one a licence, puts off the next,
the same one smile for both. Apart from the line, his
back stiff and a white goatee, stands Kishan Borana, summoned, not
come to beg. He hasn't folded his hands. Rana's been working
on him a while.
Kishan, sit, man. How long have you been standing? Good. That
land of yours by the Reva, four bigha. I'll pay one
and a half times market rate, cash. The road's coming through
there, the whole area will benefit.
The land is my forefathers', sahib. Their bones lie in it.
It's not for sale. I'm sorry.
Bones. That's good. A man should be that attached to his
land. And how's your son? Karan? He's doing pharmacy in Neemuch,
isn't he.
Something stops inside Kishan for a moment. Rana catches it and
looks away.
I hear he's started keeping company with some boys who aren't
right. The doda trade. If some case gets made tomorrow, the
boy's whole life is ruined, the licence gone too. But don't
you worry. The SP is my man. I'll tell him, Karan's
name won't come up anywhere. Completely clean.
Kishan understands it all. His back is still stiff, but something
behind his eyes has gone out.
...Should I bring the papers tomorrow?
Look at that! Kishan's a sensible man after all. Don't you
worry about the papers, I'll have them drawn up, you just
sign. And listen, Karan's remaining studies are on me now. He's
our own boy.
He sees Kishan to the stairs like an honoured guest. The
old man goes down the steps, having just signed away his
forefathers' land to save his son. Rana turns, claps for tea,
and the line shuffles one step forward.
Ratan comes inside. The compounder slumps with relief and gestures at
the money.
Sahib, I didn't even touch it, he put it there himself.
Pick it up. It isn't yours.
The compounder gathers the wad and puts it in the drawer.
Ratan goes to the tin door but doesn't open it. Beyond
it is the file he signed last autumn, on its second
page a name he never once turned back to look at.
Sugna has come and stood at the inner door. Sitting among
the women, she heard her brother's voice.
The case was cleared yesterday. We came to collect her today.
You've stopped it again.
Sugna.
She's been lying on ice four days, and now you'll take
her two hundred kilometres away to be cut open again.
The report they've made is a lie. I know how these
are made, I've been making them twenty-five years.
You know so much. When she was being sold to old
Dhanraj, a girl of sixteen, where was all this knowing of
yours then?
He has no answer. Sugna raised that girl and watched her
sold; Ratan only signed a paper.
Who killed her, Sugna?
Nobody killed her. She fell. That's what your department wrote. So
let her be cremated, brother.
She goes back into the dark. 'Nobody' sticks inside Ratan, a
little too quick, a little too certain, but he sets it
aside as a mother's grief.
A small warm room, a single tubelight. Amma on the cot
with her phone, the neighbour woman bent over, both beaming at
a photo. Manju sits to one side, eyes down, present and
absent at once. Deva comes in late, the day still riding
him: he spent the whole day with a dead girl of
sixteen, and now he's watching his sister's marriage settled on a
phone screen.
You're here! Look, a new photo of the boy came, standing
with his tractor. They've got a good bit of land in
Rajasthan. Manju will live like a queen there, a queen.
Deva looks at the photo a moment, then at his sister,
who hasn't lifted her eyes from her lap.
Is Manju looking at the photo too?
Oh, what'll she look at, she's shy, poor thing. It's a
good house, Deva. Matches like this don't come every day.
Manju lifts her eyes to her brother for a moment, then
drops them back to her lap. Deva says nothing. The girl
from the morgue is still behind his eyes, and his own
sister sits three feet away while her life is settled on
a phone.
Mid-morning, the fan turning, two farmers waiting with their files and
folded notes. The munshi is quietly on the phone, and puts
it down quickly the moment Ratan enters.
Whose call was that?
Nothing, sahib. Mishra sahib was asking whether you'd come in.
Ratan sits. The first farmer slides his file and a fold
of notes across the desk. Ratan signs the file and slides
the notes back with one finger. The farmer stares at him;
this has never happened before.
Sahib...?
Keep it. Go.
The farmer takes his money back and leaves, a little offended.
The munshi watches and says nothing. Deva, at the next desk,
is watching too.
Sahib, this body business is all over the market now. Bherulal
seth's men have been circling the hospital since morning. And Mishra
sahib has called three times.
Let them.
He pulls a file toward himself. Deva steps closer and lowers
his voice.
Sahib, what you wrote last night, that two-hundred-kilometre order, will the
body really get there? Won't those people stop it?
They'll stop it. Watch how they stop it.
Mishra stands at the window. He turns with that same usual
warmth, but he's made three calls this morning.
Sit, brother. Yesterday it seemed settled. Today I hear you've slapped
down a second order, to the district headquarters. Ratan, a report's
already in, plain and clear, death by fall. The paper's complete,
the file's closed. So what's the sense in a second post-mortem,
brother?
Because the first one came the same day.
So? The doctor was quick.
You and I have had that quickness done for twenty-five years,
Mishra. A proper post-mortem takes a week. We both know what
a same-day report means.
The warmth thins out. He tries reason; it's the one weapon
he has.
Fine, say you're right, the girl didn't fall. So what? This
system's been running twenty-five years, Ratan, before you and I came.
Now, at retirement, you'll set it straight? That girl won't come
back from ten post-mortems. Who are you doing all this for,
brother?
Ratan doesn't answer. He can't, not in any way Mishra would
understand. Mishra waits, and the silence doesn't budge the way his
silences usually do. The warmth drains from his face, and what's
underneath is just tiredness.
All right, brother. I've explained, I've done my duty. Now this
won't stay in my hands, it'll go up, to Rana sahib.
Then don't say Mishra didn't warn you.
Ratan stands. He's heard this name his whole life; this is
the man who got his father's licence cancelled. He leaves without
a word.
The house Ratan grew up beside and never once went inside.
Big, cold, full of money, somewhere a colour TV blaring, a
deep-freeze humming, papers for a new tractor on the table. Bherulal
sits at a low table counting notes, one wad, a rubber
band, the next wad, like a man counting grain. His cold-eyed
man stands waiting.
Did you give it to the hospital man?
Gave it, seth. The munshi, the compounder, all squared. Just that
Panwar...
Panwar I'll handle. He's our own man, family, he'll understand.
Sugna has come and stopped at the inner door, a steel
glass going cold in her hands. She's heard it all and
she hasn't moved. Bherulal feels her presence but doesn't look up.
You go inside. This is men's work.
How much was the deal for my daughter? Alive, she had
a price, and dead, she has one too.
I'm not the one pricing her, Sugna. The world does. I'm
just saving the house. I have a son, four years old.
His name, his licence. Should I sink the whole house over
one?
Sugna looks at him, then at the money, and goes back
into the dark of the house without a word. Bherulal looks
at the empty doorway. For a moment his hands rest on
the notes; then he ties the next wad tighter than before
and doesn't look at that door again.
And if someone asks about the girl?
She fell. Foot slipped off the embankment, hit her head. It's
been four days now, even God will write the same thing.
A white SUV stands at the gate. Bherulal stands by it,
not in mourning now but a big man solving a problem,
the cold-eyed man a step behind. The moment Ratan comes out,
he opens his arms.
Arre, sahib! There's mourning at home and you're here buried in
papers. Come, come home, have some tea. Your sister is weeping.
How did the girl fall, Bherulal?
The same thing again. Look, sahib, I'm a business man, I
talk straight. Tell me, what do you want, land, money, a
job for your boy somewhere? Whatever you say will be here
by this evening. Just end this body business right here. It's
a matter of one paper, and everything's fine.
For the truth.
Truth! Houses don't run on truth, sahib. I have a son,
four years old. Next year the licence is to be made
in his name. For that I need the family name clean,
that's all. And you, his own maternal uncle, are putting a
stain on that name, for a girl who isn't even here
anymore.
She was your own daughter.
There are other daughters. There's only one son.
He turns toward the SUV. Then he stops, as if a
small thing has come to mind, and nods not to Ratan
but to his cold-eyed man.
It's a long road, two hundred kilometres, Panwar sahib. Early morning,
deserted. A man alone, an old vehicle, anything can happen.
Last month a sahib went down this same road at night.
Bike skidded, finished on the spot. It's a bad road.
He says it without any heat. By then Bherulal is already
in the SUV, warm again, a hand raised in farewell.
Think it over. The tea will be ready.
The SUV pulls away. Tomorrow Ratan will go down that same
road.
Ratan and Deva in the hospital office. The clerk behind the
counter is very sorry but won't budge an inch.
A vehicle? There's only one hearse, sahib, and it's broken down
today, with the mechanic.
Will it be fixed by tomorrow?
Can't say, the parts come from Indore. Come back in a
week. The body will be here on ice till then, what's
the hurry.
There is a hurry. The family wants to do the last
rites and —
Any private vehicle? A tempo?
A government body in a private vehicle? There's no rule for
it, sahib. You need a form, you need approval from above.
And in cases like these, approval hasn't been coming these days.
You understand, don't you.
Ratan understands. At every door it's the same hand, two hundred
kilometres up, that never has to show its face. He doesn't
waste his anger on a small man behind a counter.
I understand.
Outside, Deva is burning with it, the way only the young
burn.
Sahib, they've stopped the vehicle deliberately. We complain higher up —
Higher up. Higher up is the very one who had the
vehicle stopped, Deva. Paper won't work anymore. We'll have to find
another way.
By the river the pyre stands ready and built, wood stacked,
ghee set out, the priest paid and sitting idle, and no
body for the pyre. The family sits around it in the
dust, the women in a circle, Sugna in the middle, dry-eyed,
while the rest weep. Bherulal's cold-eyed man moves among the men
standing at the edge, dropping a word here, a word there,
and the whole town has chosen its side. Ratan comes down
the path; the road passes right by this field and he
has to come through here. The talk stops ahead of him.
An old woman sees him and says it to his face.
He's here. This is the one. He's her own maternal uncle,
and he won't let the mother do her daughter's last rites,
four days now. Is this police rule or bandit rule?
A low murmur runs through the standing men. Ratan stops. He
looks at the empty pyre, at the wood that won't be
lit, and then past it at Sugna. For a moment his
sister turns and looks at him. She isn't begging, isn't weeping.
Then she turns her face away. Ratan walks on through that
silence, and the men make way for him.
Tempos and trucks parked for the night, the lone bulb of
a tea stall. Ratan, out of uniform, stands with a wary
tempo driver.
Four o'clock tomorrow morning, district headquarters, one trip. It's government work,
but the vehicle isn't government. The responsibility is mine.
What's to be carried, sahib?
A body.
The man's hand half closes on the money.
Bherulal seth's? Forgive me, sahib, I can't make an enemy of
that house. My business is right here. Take it today and
tomorrow my vehicles will be grounded.
He hands the money back. Ratan takes it without argument. He
knows how big a thing he's asking. Just then Deva speaks
from the dark; he came looking and heard the last part.
Sahib, my uncle has a tempo, across the border on the
Rajasthan side. He's an outsider, his business isn't here, beyond Bherulal's
grip. I'll talk to him, and I'll come along too.
Ratan looks at the boy a moment, then nods once.
Four o'clock. Don't tell anyone.
The two of them stand together a moment in the dark.
A whole different world, quite apart from the belt: a high
gate, a paved road, and a lawn kept green in a
district where the wells have run dry. Cars, men with guns
who move like police but aren't. Ratan and Deva in the
borrowed jeep. Deva takes the sprawl of it all in with
his eyes.
All this belongs to one MLA?
MLA is the recent part. Before that his father was a
bandit in the ravines. Then came the land, then the votes.
Now he hands out licences, gives to whom he likes, snatches
from whom he likes.
A man at the gate waves them in without a check;
they're expected. Ratan has gone completely still.
A wide verandah. Rana holds the centre of it on a
swing, a big carefree man in white, a phone in one
hand, a line of petitioners before him. He disposes of each
in a single breath, granting one, putting off another, never in
a hurry. The moment he sees Ratan he stands, arms open,
as if an old friend has come.
Arre, Panwar sahib! Look who's here. Come, come, sit. This is
your own home, sahib, your own home.
Ratan doesn't sit. He stands a little too long, taking in
that green lawn, the cars, those gunmen who move like police
but aren't, and Rana watches him take it all in.
My home was beyond Garoth, Rana sahib. It went with the
licence.
For half a moment the room goes quiet. Rana's smile doesn't
fall; it deepens, as if Ratan has said something dear.
Do sit. Just look at this man, that Chambal tale, the
man who went alone into the ravines among the bandits, that's
him. Your sahib was a hero in his day, beta.
I didn't come to tell tales, Rana sahib. I came to
talk about the Koteshwar girl.
Straight to business. There'll be business too, sahib. First tea, first
a little warmth. You gave the government a whole lifetime. Now
is the time to take. In the end a man should
get what is his due. Isn't that so?
A servant brings the kasumba things, opium, water, and a palm
cup. Rana takes them before the man can serve and mixes
the kasumba with his own hand, that old hospitality, refusing which
is taken as an insult.
No, no, I'll give this with my own hand. The old
way, sahib. People these days have forgotten all this, I don't
forget. This same earth gives us everything, medicine, hospitality, honour. All
from this one flower.
Ratan looks at the offered palm and doesn't take it at
once. Both know what it is: a thing taken from this
hand must be returned to this hand.
If you serve it with your own hand, then one day
you'll come asking too, Rana sahib.
For the first time Rana's pleasure is real, not for show.
He likes that the old man sees it.
See! That's exactly why you're a hero. But what a host
gives is not returned, sahib. It's the custom.
A moment. Then Ratan drinks from his hand, because in this
house, from this palm, a man does not refuse, and he
takes it the way a man finally signs a paper he's
read all the way through. Rana watches him, certain he's just
tied a thread around the old man's wrist.
The petitioners have been cleared away. Now just the two of
them, and Deva at the edge. Rana comes to it with
no change in his warmth.
Let me ask you something, don't take it badly. Your father's
licence, the one beyond Garoth, what year was it cancelled?
In seventy-eight. And it was cancelled on your father's weighing. Ask
that too, Rana sahib.
Silence. Deva is stunned. But Rana just nods slowly, sorrowful over
it, as if Ratan has reminded him of something.
It came out two kilos short, yes. The quarrels of fathers
and grandfathers, sahib. You got ground in it, and to be
honest, so did we. But that's old now. I can fix
it. One phone call, and that licence comes back in your
family's name. And that signet ring too, lying pawned at the
seth's, let it be redeemed. A man pawning his forefathers' keepsake,
it doesn't look good.
That signet ring. He even knows about the ring. Ratan's face
doesn't move, but on the wall he came in against, one
hand now rests.
The price?
Rana seems wounded by the word, as if Ratan has misread
a kindness.
Price? There's no price, sahib. I'm not getting you to do
anything. That Koteshwar girl, she fell, poor thing, that's what the
paper says too. Just let her stay fallen. Give the body
to the family, let them do the last rites. You don't
have to do anything new. What you've done for twenty-five years,
just look the other way one more time, that's all.
Rana is asking nothing of him, only to stay the same
man he's been for twenty-five years, and to look away one
more time. This goes deeper than any threat. Ratan's face doesn't
move, but on the wall he came in against, both hands
now rest.
The dead girl won't come back, sahib. But a living family,
your own, its licence can come back.
This is the very thing Ratan has wanted for twenty-five years,
set before him with warmth, in the same cup he's already
drunk from. His father's licence. That ring back on his finger.
And all of it just for one signature, which he's given
a thousand times. He's looked away for far less than this.
He looks at Rana's open, friendly face, and at that green
lawn grown on his family's dead water, and stays silent a
long time.
The girl was my niece.
Then even better. You're doing it for your own blood after
all. For family.
No.
He neither argues nor explains. He sets the empty cup down
and turns to leave. For a moment the warmth vanishes from
Rana's face. The host steps back and the thing sitting beneath
him peers out and weighs Ratan.
Think it over, Panwar sahib. Nobody's in a hurry. But don't
take too long either. Two years is a long time, and
a very short one too.
Ratan walks out through the petitioners waiting their turn. Behind him
Rana is warm again, calling the next man.
The jeep on the road, the green gate shrinking behind. Deva
is driving. He's just watched a man be offered everything, say
a single word, and walk out, and he can't hold himself
back.
Sahib, that licence was your family's. And the ring too. You
refused.
Yes.
For a girl who isn't even here anymore.
You're saying it too. Mishra says it, Bherulal says it, Rana
says it. Everyone says the same thing. Why, for a dead
girl. Nobody asks who she was for when she was alive.
Deva has no answer. He drives. He brought his whole family
to settle in a border town so his sister could marry
into a good house, and today the two halves of his
day have come face to face inside him.
A deserted highway in the dark, the tempo racing, Deva's uncle's,
with an out-of-state plate. The cloth-wrapped body is in the back.
Ratan in front, Deva in the middle, the driver hunched over
the wheel. A Bolero has been behind them a long while,
headlights steady, holding its distance.
Sahib, that Bolero. It's been on our tail since the station.
I see it.
Deva, what work have you handed me, brother. A body, and
a vehicle on our tail. I'm an outsider.
Keep driving. Don't stop, no matter what happens.
Ahead, where the road narrows over a culvert, a tractor-trolley stands
across it. Two men stand by it, putting no real effort
into moving it. Behind them the Bolero is closing in.
The road's blocked. Sahib, I was telling you —
Don't look back. Take it down into the field, run it
along the embankment.
The driver hesitates; the tempo isn't made for fields. The men
by the tractor start walking toward them. Deva is already half
out of his seat.
Deva, sit. Drive!
The driver takes the tempo off the road and onto the
shallow embankment, jolting along the field's edge, the body bouncing in
the back, and climbs back onto the road past the culvert.
The Bolero gets stuck behind the very tractor put there to
trap them. The men shout. The tempo disappears into the haze.
They came to stop us. All this for one body.
Nobody does all this for one body. The man hiding it
is afraid of something else.
Mishra on the phone, the warmth gone, just business, calling ahead
before the body arrives.
Yes, district headquarters hospital, forensics. Put me on to Doctor Khare.
...Doctor sahib, this is Mishra, from Amargarh CBN. A body's coming
to you, the Koteshwar one. Look, the case is already closed,
the report's clean. This second post-mortem is just a cranky officer's
whim, the poor man's at retirement. You understand, don't you, there's
no need to dig too much.
He listens. Whatever's said from the other end is short, and
not what he wanted. The smoothness falters.
...No, that's all right, Doctor sahib. Forgive me, sorry to trouble
you.
He hangs up and sits staring at the phone. Some doors
are so high up the road that his hand doesn't reach
them.
A big, hard hospital on the edge of the city. The
tempo comes in; Ratan and Deva carry the wrapped body inside
and no one helps. Doctor Khare meets them with a clipboard,
in his fifties, a crumpled coat, tired eyes.
The Koteshwar one? Ratan Singh Panwar. You're the one who sent
her? A call just came from Amargarh, saying don't dig too
much.
And you?
I've got six bodies today. No seth from Amargarh has done
me any favours. Whatever I see, I'll write down. I've no
time for nonsense.
For the first time the road has reached a place the
hand from above doesn't reach.
A cold room, a steel table, a drain in the floor.
Khare opens the girl with those quick, unhesitating hands that have
done this work ten thousand times. Ratan stands at the head.
Deva, by the wall, has gone pale. Khare studies him a
moment before he begins.
Female, age sixteen, seventeen. Injury to the back of the head.
...Hmm.
What is it?
Wait a moment.
He picks up the blade. At the first incision Deva turns
his face away, then walks out with a hand over his
mouth. Ratan doesn't look away. He's signed a hundred such papers
without once standing in the room. This one he stays for.
Later, the work done. Khare wipes his hands and tells them
flatly, the way he'd tell any one of the day's other
six bodies.
This girl didn't die of this head injury.
Meaning?
Meaning, when this injury was inflicted, she was already dead. There's
no blood pooled under the wound, and in a living body
it pools. Her head was struck against the embankment after death,
later. There are pressure marks on the throat, tiny blood spots
in the eyes. She was strangled. She didn't fall, she was
killed first and then made to look fallen.
What Ratan had known ever since he saw that low embankment
was finally said in a clean room, from the mouth of
a man with nothing to gain by it.
By whom?
That's your job. I can only tell you that someone killed
her up close, with their own hands. And no girl lets
a stranger get that close.
Ratan says nothing. He's thinking of a big house full of
family.
Outside, the day is a little too bright after that cold
room. Deva sits on a step, wrung out. Ratan comes out
with the folded report in his hand, two typed pages and
a stamp. Khare follows, lighting a cigarette.
Inspector, a piece of free advice. This paper is yours now.
The Amargarh people didn't want it made, which means there's a
big man's name in it, or it leads to one. I'm
two hundred kilometres away, nothing will happen to me. But you
live right among them. Be careful, sahib.
It's too late for careful now. Twenty-five years.
He doesn't explain it and Khare doesn't ask. Deva looks up
at him from the step. They've won nothing; they've only made
one thing true, and now it has to be carried.
On the way back, in a town that isn't theirs, Ratan
stops at a small post office. He photographs both pages of
the report into Deva's phone. Then he buys an envelope, writes
his own home address on it, seals the original report inside,
and posts it. A registry receipt comes across the counter and
he tucks it away carefully.
Sahib, you've got the report already. Why post it?
What's with me can be snatched, can be burned. But what's
been entered in the post, with a government stamp and date,
no one can erase now. Whatever happens to me.
Deva hears that last line and doesn't like it. Ratan walks
back toward the tempo, and the report sets off behind him
through the post, on its way home.
Very late at night. Deva has come home from the district
headquarters, that incision still in his eyes, he stood in a
cold room and watched what was done to a girl of
sixteen who said no. Amma is on the phone in the
next room, happy; the Rajasthan match is all but settled. Manju
sits with her books that she no longer opens. Deva sits
down across from her and asks the thing no one in
this house asks.
Manju. This Rajasthan match. What do you yourself want? Tell me
the truth.
Maa's seen it, hasn't she. Whatever you all think is right.
Forget Maa. I'm asking you. Do you want to go into
that house?
Manju opens her mouth and finds she has no answer ready.
No one ever taught her to have a want of her
own, let alone to speak it. She looks toward her mother's
voice from the next room.
I don't know.
It's the truest thing said in this house in weeks. Deva
looks at his sister, and the girl from the steel table
won't leave the room. He doesn't push her; he has nothing
to give her yet.
Manju has gone inside. Under Amma's glow there's a worry now;
the boy's family called after the photo went round.
There's one thing those people were saying. At the wedding the
boy needs a Bullet, a motorcycle, and a little gold. It's
a big house, their standing has to be kept up too.
A Bullet and gold. How much?
Deva, all this happens anyway. If your father were here, he
too would —
This is dowry, Maa. In plain words, dowry.
Not dowry, it's custom. It's give and take. It happens in
every house. To marry off a girl you have to give.
Why are you acting like this today?
Deva doesn't answer. He spent four days in another district learning
the market price of a girl, and now that same price
has followed him home, sat down at his own table, and
is calling itself custom.
On foot, without any paper, Ratan tracks down the village's human
rubble: Ganga, a doda-chura addict, dried up and shaking, propped against
a wall behind the country-liquor shop. A man with nothing left
to lose, and that's what makes him the only one who'll
talk.
You lie around here at night, near the fields?
Where would I go, sahib. My veins are full of doda.
I'm fit for nowhere now.
That night, Bherulal's girl's night, did you see anything?
I saw it. Late at night there was light in the
field, torches burning. Two or three men, Bherulal seth's, the big-car
ones. They were carrying something toward the embankment.
The girl?
Something heavy wrapped in cloth. I turned my face away, sahib.
Whoever keeps his eyes open at night here doesn't see the
morning. I'm half dead anyway.
Late at night. Ratan sits at his desk with the copy
of the report, working the thing out half to Deva and
half to himself.
The match with Dhanraj was settled. Bherulal's weighing had been two
kilos short for two years, the licence was shaky. The deal
over the girl would have cleared the debt and raised the
match too.
But the girl wasn't willing.
The whole village had heard her scream that she wouldn't go
to that old man. That night she died. His men laid
her on the embankment to make it look like a fall.
And in the morning they were all in a rush to
cremate her.
So you're saying Bherulal...
I'm saying every road winds back to that same house.
Deva has gone. Ratan sits alone with the picture he's drawn.
Motive, men, the cover-up, the haste, all point to that same
big house. One piece doesn't sit straight with the rest. Khare's
words: killed up close, with hands, by someone she let come
near. Bherulal's men in their big cars could carry the body
to the embankment, but no girl lets a hired man put
his hands on her throat in the dark. Whoever did this,
she knew him, and trusted him. Ratan turns the thought over
once. It leads him somewhere he isn't ready to go. He
sets it aside, tells himself the men are enough, and writes
at the top of the page: Bherulal. Below that name the
page is blank.
Ratan is out. The munshi slides a file toward Deva, a
fold of notes tucked in the cover, the daily machinery keeps
running, inspector or no inspector.
Deva, just sign this. It's an accident, a straight case. And
take this tea-money, it's your share.
Deva looks at the file, then at the money. A week
ago it would have made no difference to him. Now there's
a girl from the steel table behind his eyes, and his
sahib walking empty-handed out of a kingdom.
The file's done. You keep this.
You've caught Panwar sahib's sickness, beta? It'll wear off in two
weeks. It's a job, it doesn't run like this.
Deva says nothing. He's done nothing brave. He signed the accident
the way everyone does, just didn't take the money, and even
that small thing feels lonely.
Govind finds Ratan on the steps by the water and sits
down beside him without hurry, the way an old friend sits.
I hear you've made an enemy of the whole department. Even
Rana. For a dead girl.
You've come to say the same thing too?
No. I've come to say it's good to see you like
this after years. For twenty-five years you walked around dead, Ratan.
A corpse in uniform. Now something's stirring inside you. You've picked
a bad time for it, two years left, the pension on
the line. But the topsoil's coming off. Underneath is the same
old man.
Maybe it's coming off too late.
Late is fine. We all have to die, Ratan. Some people
just wake up once before they do.
On the way back. Deva has carried this whole day, the
dowry sat at his table, and the money he didn't take,
and now it comes out.
Sahib, today I didn't take the money from munshi-ji. But I
know, in two weeks I'll start taking it. Everyone does, you
took it too. So what difference does it make? One girl,
one report, what will it change? You're wrecking your whole life
and nothing will change.
Ratan walks a while before he answers, and what he gives
the boy is no hero's answer, because he doesn't have one.
Nothing will change. And there's no profit in it either.
Then why are you doing it?
For twenty-five years I signed every body and went home, ate,
and slept. This time I couldn't sleep. That's all it is.
He says nothing more. At the turn where their paths part,
he stops, and without looking at the boy, says:
The day your own sleep goes too, don't run from it.
That's the one thing that'll stay alive in you.
He walks away. Deva stands a long while at that turn.
Bherulal has come to him, and this time the seth isn't
calm, the report's reached the district, the body's been cut, and
Panwar is still going. Rana hears him out from his swing,
feeding pieces of fruit to a bird shut in a cage.
Rana sahib, this is slipping out of hand. The report's made,
it's reached the district. That man won't stop. You said you'd
handle it.
I am handling it.
Until when, sahib? He's my son, the licence is to be
made in his name next year...
I offered that man his father's cancelled licence back, Bherulal. Served
him kasumba with my own hand. And he said no to
my face.
He watches the bird hop in the cage.
Very few people say no to me. And those who do,
I remember them.
He picks up the phone, and the warmth that returns is
just a habit his face goes through.
Yes, listen. That Koteshwar matter, the Panwar one. The man's tired,
poor thing, at retirement. All this running about isn't good for
the health. Get him a little rest. At home.
He sets the phone down and turns back to the bird.
He never says the word 'suspension'; there are other people for
that.
Mishra brings the order himself, which in its own way is
a kindness. He isn't gloating. He's genuinely pained, and that's harder
to bear.
You've been suspended, inquiry pending. I told you, Ratan, this went
all the way up. Hand in your badge and revolver. And
the pension will stay frozen till the inquiry's complete. And the
inquiry never completes, you know that.
Ratan unclips the badge and lays it on the desk. Twenty-five
years. He doesn't argue. There's no one to argue with, only
Mishra, who is himself just a man the machine uses.
Done?
Done. Now let it go, yaar. The badge is gone, the
pension's going too. Now for whom?
Ratan doesn't answer. For the first time in twenty-five years he
turns and walks out without a badge. Mishra is left looking
at what's left on the desk.
Ratan at home, without a badge. Kanta has heard; the town
hears everything. She serves the food, but today there's an edge
in it that the silent years had kept down. The pension
papers, which he'd left in a drawer, lie out on the
table today.
The office women came today. They were asking if it's true,
that there's been a suspension, the pension frozen. I said, how
would I know. My husband never tells me anything.
Kanta.
Two years. Just two years were left. You thought the same
thing too, a little peace after two years. And you blew
it all in one stroke. For a dead girl you don't
even know.
She's said the thing she never says. The kitchen goes completely
silent. Ratan looks at the papers, and at his wife, who
gave up expecting anything of him years ago and today waits
for an answer. He can't give her the true answer, that
the girl was his sister's child, that he sold her on
paper without seeing her. He gives her what he has.
I know her. And I don't, either.
It's no answer and she knows it. But underneath it she
hears something that hasn't been in his voice for twenty-five years,
the man she married, who was different before the dust settled.
This frightens her more than the lost pension. This time she
doesn't put the papers back. She sits down across from him,
which she hasn't done in years, and slides the plate a
little closer.
Eat. It's getting cold.
Ratan on a bench in a senior officer's outer room, a
file on his knee, an old man in plain clothes, no
badge. A PA passes him twice. The third time he stops,
plainly told what to say.
Sahib is in a meeting. And anyway you're suspended now, aren't
you, officially you can't bring any case. Send your complaint by
post, it'll be looked into.
By post.
Yes. That's the rule.
Ratan looks at that closed door, behind which a man he
worked under for years won't see him. He spent his life
inside these very doors, watching them close on others. He stands,
tucks the file under his arm, and leaves.
Without a badge, without any way, outside every book. Ratan stands
across the dark field from the big house, glittering at the
far end. His sister's house, the house his theory points to.
Deva comes and stands beside him, out of uniform too.
Sahib, you're suspended. I'll get caught up in this with you.
Go home, Deva. This is my fight.
You're the one who said, the day your sleep goes, don't
run from it. Mine's gone, sahib.
Ratan doesn't send him back again. The two of them stand
watching that glittering house across the dark.
Bherulal. From tomorrow we start with that house.
Inside those glittering windows his sister sits, and her brother stands
out here in the dark, deciding to start with the wrong
man.
A man walking home through the dark, sleeping belt, without a
badge, without a pension, without any way, a file under his
arm and a registry receipt in his pocket. By every measure
of this place he's been beaten. He's blown those two years,
the pension, his place, his wife's peace, all of it. By
every rule of the principles he lived by, this is the
place where a man stops.
He doesn't stop.
The Jhujhar song rises, the voice of the Charan, of the
headless one who keeps fighting even after he's fallen.
Last image: the old man alone on a dark road, walking
toward that glittering house.
The curtain falls.